# Maitraye Das

maitraye.github.io maitraye@u.northwestern.edu

#### **Research Statement**

My research interest falls broadly in the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), and Accessibility. Specifically, my doctoral research involves studying and designing for accessible collaborative content production in ability-diverse teams. My work draws on literature in HCI, CSCW, and critical disability studies to uncover how accessibility is created, negotiated, and sustained in collaborative work. Methodologically, I take a cross-disciplinary approach that includes qualitative methods (e.g., contextual interviews, observations, ethnography) as well as system design, development, and evaluation through controlled experiments and design exploration studies. As a HCI researcher, my broader goal is to support accessibility through design and thus, contribute towards reducing equity gaps in education, employment, and creative expression.

#### **Education**

#### NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

EVANSTON, IL, USA

PhD in Technology and Social Behavior (Computer Science & Communication)

Fall 2017 - Present

Dissertation: Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments Committee: Darren Gergle (chair), Anne Marie Piper (co-chair), Marcelo Worsley, and Cynthia Bennett

#### NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

EVANSTON, IL, USA

**MS** in **Technology and Social Behavior** (Computer Science & Communication) *GPA*: 3.97 out of 4.00

Mar 2021

BANGLADESH UNIVERSITY OF ENGINEERING & TECHNOLOGY (BUET)

BANGLADESH

BS in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) with Honors

Sep 2015

GPA: 3.85 out of 4.00 (top 6% of the graduating class)

## Research Experience

# COLLABORATIVE TECHNOLOGY LAB $\mid$ NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

Fall 2017 - Present

# $\textbf{Graduate Research Assistant} \ | \ \text{advised by } \textbf{Darren Gergle}$

- Conducted contextual interviews and observations to understand collaborative writing practices and accessibility needs of visually impaired writers. Developed audio enhancements for asynchronous collaborative writing and evaluated through a mixed-methods controlled experimental study. Currently developing non-visual interactions to support accessibility in synchronous collaborative writing for visually impaired writers. [CSCW 2019] Faculty collaborator: Anne Marie Piper
- Collected a dataset of nearly 0.45 billion edits by 2000 OpenStreetMap editors using Python and Osmium.
   Performed quantitative analysis to investigate gender-based self-focus bias in OpenStreetMap. [CHI 2019]
   Faculty collaborator: Brent Heeht

## INCLUSIVE TECHNOLOGY LAB | NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

Spring 2018 - Present

#### Graduate Researcher | advised by Anne Marie Piper

Conducted ethnographic field observations and contextual interviews at a weaving studio for people with vision
impairments. Designed auditory augmentations on a loom to enhance collaborative weaving experiences among
blind weavers and their sighted instructors. Currently developing an audio-tactile system to support collaborative
designing of fabric patterns for blind weavers. [CHI 2020, TACCESS 2021]

# ABILITY TEAM | MICROSOFT RESEARCH, USA

Summer 2020

# Research Intern | mentored by John Tang

 Conducted semi-structured interviews with 36 neurodivergent professionals. Performed thematic analysis to highlight accessibility issues in remote work during the COVID-19 pandemic. [CSCW 2021] Collaborators: Kathryn Ringland, Anne Marie Piper

#### WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, USA

Summer 2017

# Researcher (remote) | mentored by Moushumi Sharmin and Shameem Ahmed

Performed a systematic literature review on the design of smart technologies for children on the autism spectrum.
 [CHI 2018]

Maitraye Das | p. 1 Last updated 4/5/21

# Undergraduate Researcher | advised by Tanzima Hashem

 Developed a secret sharing algorithm for privacy-preserved and authenticated queries in genomic databases to compute disease susceptibility. [COMPSAC 2018, Journal of Information Processing 2019]

#### Honors, Awards, & Grants

Graduate Research Grant   Northwestern University (\$2,999)	2021
Finalist (top 20)   Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship	2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award   ACM CHI [C1]	2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award   ACM CSCW [J4]	2019
Special Recognition for Outstanding Review   ACM CHI'21 (3 times), ACM CSCW'19	2021, 2019
Conference Travel Grant   Northwestern University (\$2,300 + \$1,500)	2019, 2018
Best Paper Award   IEEE COMPSAC [C4]	2018
Student Travel Grant   ACM UbiComp (\$600)	2018
Student Scholarship   Grace Hopper Celebration, USA	2018
Best Undergraduate Thesis Award   Dept. of CSE, Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2015
Best Technical Poster   Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014
Student Scholarship   Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014
Dean's List Award   Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2011 - 2015
University Merit Scholarship   Bangladesh University of Engg. & Technology	2011 - 2014

#### Journal Articles<sup>1</sup>

- J1. **Maitraye Das,** Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. Design and Evaluation of Collaborative Writing Techniques for People with Vision Impairments. Under review in *ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI)*. [Impact Factor: 3.147]
- J2. Maitraye Das, John Tang, Kathryn E. Ringland, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Towards Accessible Remote Work: Understanding Work-from-Home Practices of Neurodivergent Professionals. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*, Vol. 5, CSCW1, Article 183 (April 2021), 30 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3449282
- J3. Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, Maitraye Das, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Melodie: A Design Inquiry into Accessible Crafting through Audio-Enhanced Weaving. In ACM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS), Vol. 14, 1, Article 5 (March 2021), 30 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3444699 [Impact Factor: 2.641]
- Q J4. Maitraye Das, Darren Gergle, and Anne Marie Piper. 2019. "It doesn't win you friends": Understanding Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction*, Vol. 3, CSCW, Article 191 (November 2019), 26 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3359293 [acceptance rate: 31.2%]
  - \*Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions).
  - J5. Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Maitraye Das, Tanzima Hashem, Sharmin Afrose, and Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar. 2019. Towards Privacy-preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries. In *Journal of Information Processing*, Vol. 27, (September 2019), pp. 624-642. DOI: 10.2197/ipsjjip.27.624

## **Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers**

- **Q** C1. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Weaving by Touch: A Case Analysis of Accessible Making. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20),* 1-15. DOI: 10.1145/3313831.3376477 [acceptance rate: 24.3%]
  - \*Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions).
  - C2. Maitraye Das, Brent Hecht, and Darren Gergle. 2019. The Gendered Geography of Contributions to OpenStreetMap: Complexities in Self-Focus Bias. In *Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '19)*, Paper 563, 14 pages. DOI: 10.1145/3290605.3300793 [acceptance rate: 23.8%]

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup> <u>Top-tier publication venues in Human-Computer Interaction</u> research include peer-reviewed conferences such as CHI and CSCW and journals such as TOCHI. Since 2018, CSCW transitioned to a hybrid journal structure. These venues are highly selective, extensively reviewed, and intended for archival papers only. When available, the acceptance rate is included.

- C3. Moushumi Sharmin, Monsur Hossain, Abir Saha, **Maitraye Das**, Margot Maxwell, and Shameem Ahmed. 2018. From Research to Practice: Informing the Design of Autism Support Smart Technology. In *Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '18)*, Paper 102, 1-16. DOI: 10.1145/3173574.3173676 [acceptance rate: 25%]
- P C4. Maitraye Das, Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Sharmin Afrose, Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar, and Tanzima Hashem.
  2018. A Novel Secret Sharing Approach for Privacy-Preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries in
  Genomic Databases. In Proceedings of the 42<sup>nd</sup> IEEE International Conference on Computers, Software, and Applications
  (COMPSAC '18), pp. 645-654. DOI: 10.1109/COMPSAC.2018.00097 [acceptance rate: 24%]

  \*Best Paper Award
  - C5. Abir Saha and **Maitraye Das**. 2017. Impact of Social Networking on Post-Partum Depression in Women: An Analysis in the context of Bangladesh. In *Proceedings of the 20th IEEE International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '17)*, pp. 1-6. DOI: 10.1109/ICCITECHN.2017.8281831
  - C6. **Maitraye Das** and Abir Saha. 2017. An Automated Speech-Language Therapy Tool with Interactive Virtual Agent and Peer-to-Peer Feedback. In *Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE '17)*, pp. 510-515, DOI: 10.1109/ICAEE.2017.8255409
  - C7. Fatema Khan, **Maitraye Das**, and Ahiya Ahammed. 2016. PurpleAid: An mHealth platform to combat health hazards of women. In *Proceedings of the 2016 International Conference on Medical Engineering, Health Informatics and Technology (MediTec '16*), pp. 1-6. DOI: 10.1109/MEDITEC.2016.7835368
  - C8. **Maitraye Das**, Sunandita Sarker, and Syeda Lammim Ahad. 2016. A Novel Health Support System with Biometric Data Acquisition Device. In *Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '16)*, pp. 201-206. DOI: 10.1109/ICCITECHN.2016.7860195

# Refereed Workshop Short Papers, Posters, and Doctoral Consortia

- 1. **Maitraye Das.** 2020. Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In 2020 Conference Companion Publication on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '20). DOI: 10.1145/3406865.3418369 [Doctoral Consortium]
- 2. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Rethinking Power and Politics in Accessible Making. In *ACM CHI Workshop* "Nothing About Us Without Us": Investigating the Role of Critical Disability Studies in HCI.
- Maitraye Das. 2019. Who Can See What: Privacy and Audience Management for People with Vision Impairments on Social Media. In ACM CSCW Workshop on Addressing the Accessibility of Social Media.
- Maitraye Das. 2018. Understanding Collaborative Writing Practices of People with Visual Impairments. In Proceedings of the 2018 ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp '18), pp. 1744-1749. DOI: 10.1145/3267305.3277807
- 5. **Maitraye Das**. 2018. Towards Understanding the Effects of Social Networking on Postpartum Depression in Women. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing*, USA.
- 6. **Maitraye Das**, Sharmin Afrose, and Tanzima Hashem. 2015. Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing*, USA.
- Maitraye Das, Sunandita Sarker, and Shahina Ferdous. 2014. SpeechAid: A Self-treatment System for Individuals with Speech Disorder. In *Grace Hopper Celebration India*.
   \*Best Technical Poster Award

# **Teaching Experience**

UNITED INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY (UIU)

DHAKA, BANGLADESH Oct 2015 - Mar 2017

Lecturer | Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

 Instructed courses on Computer Architecture, Digital Logic Design, Electrical Circuits and Assembly Programming Language.

#### Skills

Vice-President

Murchhona: BUET (cultural club)

**Programming:** Python, R, C, C++, Java, HTML, CSS Research Methods: Interviews, contextual observations, ethnography, thematic analysis, grounded theory method, survey design, experiment design, quantitative analysis, prototyping **Students Mentored** Thomas McHugh | Undergrad in Computer Science, Northwestern University 2020 - Present Rawan Mohamed | Undergrad in Computer Science, Northwestern University 2020 Caroline Brewley | High school student researcher 2019 Nusrat Jahan Mozumder | Undergrad in CSE, Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology 2017 - 2018 Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar | Undergrad in CSE, Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology 2017 - 2018 Fatema Khan | Undergrad in CSE, United International University 2016 Ahiya Ahammed | Undergrad in CSE, United International University 2016 **Invited Talks** Input and Interaction (INFO 463) | University of Washington Nov 2020 Guest lecture: Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments (virtual) Bangladesh HCI and ICTD Study and Research Group, Virtual Event Apr 2020 Talk: Designing for Accessible Interaction Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship Finalist Presentation | Redmond, WA, USA Nov 2019 Poster: Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments **Academic Services Program Committee Member** Shadow PC, ACM COMPASS 2021 Reviewer ACM CHI [\*outstanding review recognitions: 3] 2021 IEEE COMPSAC 2021 ACM CSCW [\*outstanding review recognition: 1] 2020, 2019 **ACM DIS** 2020 GHC Faculty Scholarship 2017 Australasian Database Conference 2016 **Student Volunteer** ACM CHI 2021, 2019 ACM CSCW 2019 ACM UbiComp 2018 InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University 2018 **Publicity Co-chair** InfoSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University 2019 **Outreach & Memberships** 2020 - Present Co-host & Co-organizer Inspiring Stories (podcast series on Bangladeshi women in STEM) Member Northwestern Graduate Women in Computing 2019 - Present Association for Computing Machinery (ACM), SIGCHI, SIGACCESS 2017 - Present 2015 - Present Bangladeshi Women in Computer Science and Engineering Code Coach Volunteer BraveCamp Chicago (non-profit coding camp for high school girls) Summer 2018

2014 - 2015